Guide to the John Ferguson Weir Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1861-1928, 1939; Series I; 2.5; (5 boxes)
  - Correspondence (by Individual Name Folder)
    - Walker, C. Howard (3), 1907 (Box 5, Folder 128)
    - Walker, John Brisben (1), 1893 (Box 5, Folder 128)
    - Ware, William Robert (14), 1878-1879, 1891, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 129)
    - Warren, H. Langford (3), 1900, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 129)
    - Warren, John Collins (1), 1901 (Box 5, Folder 130)
    - Warren, Whitney (1), 1906 (Box 5, Folder 130)
    - Watrous, Eliot (1), 1906 (Box 5, Folder 131)
    - Watrous, George D. (4), 1906, 1908, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 131)
    - Watrous, Henry W. (2), 1901 (Box 5, Folder 131)
    - Weir, John Ferguson (to unidentified correspondents)(6), undated (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - Weir, Mary French (typed copies) (51), 1861-1862, 1864-1866, 1876, 1879-1881, 1893-1894, 1897, 1902, 1913, undated (Box 5, Folder 133)
    - Weir, Julian Alden (typed copies) (102), 1875-1877, 1880, 1882-1883, 1889-1895, 1899, 1901-1904, 1906, 1910, 1912-1916, 1918-1919 (Box 5, Folder 134)
    - Weir, Robert (10), 1869, undated (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - Weir, Robert Walter (4), 1869, 1875, undated (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - Welch, Lewis (2), 1895 (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - Wheeler, J. Davenport (13), 1882, 1893, 1909-1911, 1919, undated (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - Whittredge, Worthington (1), 1897 (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - Wight, Peter Bonnett (3), 1871, 1899, 1902 (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - Wolf, Henry (2), 1909-1910 (Box 5, Folder 139)
    - Wood, Thomas W. (2), 1896-1897 (Box 5, Folder 139)
    - Woolsey, Theodore S. (5), 1885, 1899, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 140)
    - Wright, Henry P. (7), 1904, 1907-1908 (Box 5, Folder 140)
    - Yacobian, Loutfi D. (12), 1906-1908 (Box 5, Folder 141)
    - Yale University (11), 1879, 1891, 1896, 1902, 1906, 1909, 1912, 1924, undated (Box 5, Folder 142)
    - Yale University, Sheffield Scientific School (3), 1893 (Box 5, Folder 143)
    - Yale University, Yale School of the Fine Arts (5), 1908, 1911-1912 (Box 5, Folder 144)
  - M. F. Weir Correspondence
    - Alden, Sarah (1), undated (Box 5, Folder 145)
    - Field, Charles W. (1), 1926 (Box 5, Folder 145)
    - French, John W. (1), 1870, undated (Box 5, Folder 145)
    - Gifford, Mary (2), 1869, 1871 (Box 5, Folder 145)
    - Griffis, William E. (1), 1926 (Box 5, Folder 145)
    - McEntee, Gertrude and Jervis (5), 1868-1869, undated (Box 5, Folder 146)
    - Perry, James DeW. (1), 1926 (Box 5, Folder 146)
    - Thompson, Launt (1), 1869 (Box 5, Folder 146)
    - Vose, Helen W. (1), 1926 (Box 5, Folder 146)
    - unidentified (4), 1869, 1903, 1926, n. (Box 5, Folder 146)
  - E. Weir Perry Correspondence
    - A, F, L, N (4), 1927-1928, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - Brewster, Chauncey B. (1), 1926 (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - Conover, James P. (1), 1926 (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - Pressey, William, (1), 1926 (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - Vance, W. H. P. (1), 1926 (Box 5, Folder 147)
- ADDRESSES AND WRITINGS, mostly undated; Series II; 2; (4 boxes)
  The material in this section is arranged alphabetically by title. The date is noted where possible.
  - "American Art: Its Progress and Prospects", 1878 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "American Landscape Painters", 1873 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - "The Architect and his Art", 1882 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "The Architectural Influence of the World's Columbian Exposition", undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - "Art in Worship", 1885 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - "Art Study at Home and Abroad", 1883 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - "The Artist as Painter", 1883 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - "Classicism in Modern French Art", 1907 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - "Composition", undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - "Constable", undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Albrecht Dürer, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - An Evening in Venice", undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - "Expression", undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - G. P. Fisher Memorial Window, 1914 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - "The Florentine Renaissance", 1873 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - "The Florentine Renaissance in Art", 1896 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - "Francis of Assisi", undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - "Gainsborough and Raeburn", undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - "Sanford R. Gifford", 1880 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - "Handicraft", undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - The Jarves Collection of Italian Paintings", undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - "Meissonier", undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - "Michaelangelo", undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Jean François Millet, 1909 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - "Naturalism in Modern French Art", 1907 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - "A New Chapter in Psychology", undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - "The Painter's Art", 1882 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - G. H. Palmer's George Herbert, undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Plastic and Graphic Art at the 1876 International Exhibition, 1877 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - "Popular Art Education", 1881 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - "The Principles and Means of Art", undated (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - "Raphael and his Time", 1904 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - "The Relation of Art to Religion and Life", 1906 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - "Rembrandt", undated (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - "Sir Joshua Reynolds", undated (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - "Romanticism in Modern French Art", undated (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - "Romney, Hoppner, and Lawrence", undated (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - "The Sculptor and his Art", 1881 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - "Some Distinctions between Literary and Other Forms of Art", undated (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - "Some Reasons for a Belief in the Possibility of Miracles", undated (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - "Some Relations Between the Arts", undated (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - "The Student of Art", undated (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Studies for Paintings, undated (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - Systems of Training in Art Schools, undated (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Translation of Véron's "The Situation of Art in France", undated (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - "The True Place of Art in Christianity", 1876 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - "Turner", undated (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - "Velasquez", 1909 (Box 8, Folder 48)
  - J. F. Weir's Memoirs: "Memories of West Point, part one" (typescript) (Box 9, Folder 49)
  - J. F. Weir's Memoirs: "Memories of West Point, part one" (rough draft and notes) (Box 9, Folder 50)
  - J. F. Weir's Memoirs: "Memories of West Point, part two" (typescript) (Box 9, Folder 51)
  - J. F. Weir's Memoirs: "Memories of West Point, part two" (rough draft and notes) (Box 9, Folder 52)
  - J. F. Weir's Memoirs: "The Tenth Street Studios" (typescript) (Box 9, Folder 53)
  - J. F. Weir's Memoirs: "The Tenth Street Studios" (rough draft and notes) (Box 9, Folder 54)
  - J. F. Weir's Memoirs: "The Tenth Street Studios and Abroad" (typescript) (Box 9, Folder 55)
  - J. F. Weir's Memoirs: "The Tenth Street Studios and Abroad" (rough draft and notes) (Box 9, Folder 56)
  - J. F. Weir's Memoirs: "Memories of a Yale Professor, 1869-1913" (typescript) (Box 9, Folder 57)
  - J. F. Weir's Memoirs: "Memories of a Yale Professor, 1869-1913" (fragments of MSS.) (Box 9, Folder 58)
  - J. F. Weir's Memoirs: "Memories of a Yale Professor, 1869-1913" (rough draft and notes) (Box 9, Folder 59)
  - J. F. Weir's Memoirs: "Conclusion" (typescript and rough draft) (Box 9, Folder 60)
  - "What Did the Apostle Paul Mean?", 1890 (Box 10, Folder 61)
  - "The Yale Collection of Casts", undated (Box 10, Folder 62)
  - "The Yale Collections of Greek, Roman and Renaissance Sculpture", undated (Box 10, Folder 63)
  - Yale School of the Fine Arts, Anniversary Addresses, 1891, 1903, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 64)
  - Yale School of the Fine Arts, Anniversary Addresses, 1908-1913 (Box 10, Folder 65)
  - Yale School of the Fine Arts, Fiftieth Anniversary Address, 1916 (Box 10, Folder 66)
- PAPERS, PLANS, AND NOTES RE: YALE SCHOOL OF FINE ARTS, mostly undated; Series III; 0.25; (1 box)
  The miscellaneous notes and numerous rough drafts of plans, proposals and memos in this section have been broadly grouped together according to their subject. Also filed in this section are papers dealing with the founding and development of the Yale School of the Fine Arts and catalogues, programs, and syllabi of the School.
  - Papers re: gift of A. R. Street and founding of Yale School of the Fine Arts (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Notes and memos re: organization of Yale School of the Fine Arts (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Catalogues and course information (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Notes on courses (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Proposal and notes for architecture course (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Memos and notes re: finances (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Reports of the Yale School of the Fine Arts (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Lecture announcements and syllabi (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Lists and notes re: fellowships and prizes (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Notes and plans for anniversary observances (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Lists and notes re: exhibitions (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Exhibition programs (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Remarks on plans for library and for University Hall (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Statement of J. F. Weir in reply to charges of D. Cady Eaton (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Papers and notes on memorials and medals (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 10, Folder 16)
- PERSONAL PAPERS AND MEMORABILIA, Series IV
  - Account book of J. F. Weir, 1858-1869 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Bills and receipts, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Biographical material on J. F. Weir, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Oversize, undated (Box 14)
  - Calling cards and invitations, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Diaries of European trip, 1869 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Notes on European trip, [1869?] (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Passport of J. F. Weir, 1868 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Promotional materials for J. F. Weir's lectures, paintings, and writings, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Sketchbook of J. F. Weir, undated (Box 11, Folder 9-10)
  - Sketches and plans of J. F. Weir, undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Address book containing lists of works by J. F. Weir, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Lists of works by J. F. Weir, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Catalogues of Works of J. Alden Weir and Robert W. Weir, undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Magazine clippings, 1903, 1907, 1909-1910, 1913-1914, 1926, 1940, undated (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1898, 1901-1903, 1905, 1907-1909, 1911, 1925-1926, undated (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Reviews of J. F. Weir's The Way: The Nature and Means of Revelation, 1889 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Reviews of J. F. Weir's Human Destiny in the Life of Revelation, 1903 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Reviews of J. F. Weir's Revelation and the Life to Come, 1916 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Photographs of Bennington Battle Monument, undated (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Photographs of Woolsey Statue, undated (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Photographs of J. F. Weir, family, and friends, undated (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Photographs of J. F. Weir's studio, undated (Box 14)
  - Misc. photographs and negatives, undated (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Notes and writings of Mary French Weir, undated (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - Oversize (Box 14)
- BICENTENNIAL ART EXHIBITION, Series V
  These papers were originally in Yale MSS Yale A.
  - Letters to John F. Weir and others concerning loans for the Bicentennial art exhibition
    - A-B, 1901 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - C, 1901 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - D, 1901 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - E-G, 1901 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - H-J, 1901 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - L, 1901 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - M-N, 1901 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - O-Q, 1901 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - S-T, 1901 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - V-W, 1901 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Handwritten notes of the record of loans for the Bicentennial art exhibit, 1901 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Notes on insurance and insurance policies for loans for the Bicentennial art exhibit, 1901 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, bills, receipts pertaining to the packing and shipping of loans for the Bicentennial art exhibit, 1901 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Notes about paintings and possible loans for the Bicentennial art exhibit, 1901 (Box 13, Folder 14)
- Additional Material, Accession 1978-M-003
  - J. F. Weir Biography [from Matthews American Armory and Blue Book?] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters from John F. Weir to family members and others
    - [1862? - 1867], 1877 - 1923 (Box 1, Folder 2-6)
  - Letters to John F. Weir
    - 1859-1868, undated, 1869-1925, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-16)
  - Letters [mostly to Mary (French) Weir, some to others]
    - 1850 - 1861 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1862 [includes a watercolor sketch in correspondence] (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 1864 - 1866, 1879 - 1889, 1891 - 1899, 1901 - 1903 - 1909, 1912 - 1925 (Box 1, Folder 19-26)
  - Poetry written by John William French, Mary (French) Weir, and unidentified, 1838, 1914, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 4 clippings of J. F. Weir's letters to newspapers, 1878, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Obituaries on friends, 1880, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Note and notebooks of house and garden records, 1855-1856 undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Notes, notebook, lists related to building and landscaping "The cottage", 1854, 1856, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Journals and pocket diaries, 1862-1897, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Journal, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Diary with sketches, account book, dictionary, book of pressed leaves (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Memorabilia: clipping, calling cards, card printing plate, poem by Mary F. Weir (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Lectures on art and teaching at Yale circa 1870-1926; clippings, pamphlets, tickets, advertisements (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Memorabilia regarding purchase and publicity for works, exhibitions, circa 1865-1962; tickets, pamphlets, invitations, clippings, postcards, correspondence (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Advertisements for J. F. Weir's lectures and publications (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence between DeWolf Perry and Theodore Sizer, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Letters, calling cards, pamphlets, invitations, memorabilia, clippings (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Clipping from The News of the Highlands regarding Robert W. Weir's house, 1973 February 22 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Legal papers: correspondence, 1888-1925 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Legal and financial papers
    - Agreement with G. P. Putnam & Sons, 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Life insurance policy, receipts, correspondence, 1884-1901 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Accounts and inventory, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Receipts, correspondence, bank book, 1914-1926 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Legal Papers
    - Correspondence, receipts, deed regarding burial plot and dispersal of goods from an estate (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - agreement with Houghton, Mifflin & Co. for publication of "The Way: The Nature as Means of Revelation", 1888 October (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Wills (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Mesmeric Experiments and Seances, 1880-1881 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Notes on Prayer and Faith, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Nature and the Spirit, or Science and Revelation; manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Revelation and the Life to Come; typescript (140 pp.), Circa 1913 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Nature and the Spirit, or Science and Revelation (manuscript of text), undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - "St. Francis and The Twentieth Century" by J. F. Weir; annotated typescript (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - 4 notebooks containing "Religious and Philosophical Reflections", 1882-1888 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - 2 notebooks containing "Religious and Philosophical Reflections", undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Historical Address for the Fiftieth Anniversary of the School of Fine Arts by J. F. Weir, 1916 June 19 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - "The Recollections of John Ferguson Weir," edited by Theodore Sizer; typescript, [c. 1957?] (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - JFW sketchbook 8 1/4" x 10 7/8", undated (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - JFW music sketchbook 6 3/4" x 9", undated (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - JFW or E. W. Perry sketchbook 4 3/4" x 6 3/4", 1902 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - JFW sketchbook - Italy 4 5/8" x 6 1/4", 1869 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - JFW sketchbook - Italy, including several water color sketches 5 7/8" x 9 1/8", 1869 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - JFW sketchbook 7 3/8" x 10", 1863 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - "Army Wagons;" Drawing by John F. Weir, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Studies for medals and plaques (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Sketches, watercolors, drawings, pastel and oil on paper, 1862-1887, undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Drawings, 1856-1913 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Watercolors, undated (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Sketches, watercolor, drawings, oil on paper, 1904, undated (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Watercolor 13 1/8" x 9 3/4", 1908 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Self-portrait, John F. Weir (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Study for "Autumn Lights," oil on canvas, with clippings and note [from Dewolf Perry?] (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Oil colors on canvas and papers, Landscape of Venice; Landscape (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Portrait drawings of JFW (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Unidentified oil on wood (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Large envelope: "In all probability a very early painting by John F. Weir of a scene near West Point of the kind he sold to cadets." Fragile (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - "The Samuel T. Shaw Collection," auction catalogue, #164 is a JFW painting, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - The National Gazette, shipbuilding Number; JFW painting as cover, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - International Studio, p. 29 is a dry-point of JFW by J. Alden Weir, 1926 September (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Fortune, p. 102 is a painting of JFW, 1940 February (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Printed matter with notes, "What did the Apostle Paul Mean?" from New Englander and Yale Review (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Photographs taken at Newburg on Hudson containing John F. Weir, undated (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Photograph in frame of John F. Weir (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Photograph taken at Newburg on Hudson containing John F. Weir, undated (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Negative photostats of J. F. Weir paintings, photographs, and Yale related material? (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Photographs of work (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Maps, clippings, photographs, postcards of foreign and domestic scenes, buildings, paintings, locations (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Scrapbook-clippings on exhibitions, lectures, etc. (Box 4, Folder 82)
- Additional Material, Accession 2002-M-047
  This accession consists of photographs of selected paintings and sculptures by John F. Weir. Photographs of Weir and his studio are included. Subjects are listed alphabetically by personal name, title of work, or subject.
  - Brush, G. F., undated (Box 1)
  - Burnett Fountain, undated (Box 1)
  - The Cellist, undated (Box 1)
  - Chittenden, Russell Henry, undated (Box 1)
  - Church confessional, undated (Box 1)
  - Lafayette, undated (Box 1)
  - Palissy, B., undated (Box 1)
  - Michaux, F. A., undated (Box 1)
  - Miss Paul--, undated (Box 1)
  - Mitchell, Donald Grant, undated (Box 1)
  - Sabatier, Paul, undated (Box 1)
  - Silliman, Benjamin, Jr., undated (Box 1)
  - Stokes, Anson Phelps, Jr., undated (Box 1)
  - Studio of Robert Weir at West Point, [1864?] (Box 1)
  - Studio of John Weir at Yale Art School, undated (Box 1)
  - Theological faculty group, Yale, 1881 (Box 1)
  - Ved--, Elihu, 1902 (Box 1)
  - Weir, John Ferguson, undated (Box 1)
  - Woolsey, Theodore Dwight, undated (Box 1)
  - Unidentified landscapes, undated (Box 1)